<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>railo on dronesec</title>
    <link>https://dronesec.pw/categories/railo/</link>
    <description>Recent content in railo on dronesec</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Bryan Alexander</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 27 Aug 2014 15:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://dronesec.pw/categories/railo/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>railo security - part four - pre-auth remote code execution</title>
      <link>https://dronesec.pw/blog/railo-security-part-four-pre-auth-remote-code-execution/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Aug 2014 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dronesec.pw/blog/railo-security-part-four-pre-auth-remote-code-execution/</guid>
      <description>Part one - intro
Part two - post-auth rce
Part three - pre-auth password retrieval
Part four - pre-auth remote code execution
This post concludes our deep dive into the Railo application server by detailing not only one, but two pre-auth remote code execution vulnerabilities. If you&amp;rsquo;ve skipped the first three parts of this blog post to get to the juicy stuff, I don&amp;rsquo;t blame you, but I do recommend going back and reading them; there&amp;rsquo;s some important information and details back there.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>railo security - part three - pre-authentication LFI</title>
      <link>https://dronesec.pw/blog/railo-security-part-three-pre-authentication-lfi/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Aug 2014 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dronesec.pw/blog/railo-security-part-three-pre-authentication-lfi/</guid>
      <description>Part one - intro
Part two - post-authentication rce
Part three - pre-authentication LFI
Part four - pre-authentication rce
This post continues our four part Railo security analysis with three pre-authentication LFI vulnerabilities. These allow anonymous users access to retrieve the administrative plaintext password and login to the server&amp;rsquo;s administrative interfaces. If you&amp;rsquo;re unfamiliar with Railo, I recommend at the very least reading part one of this series. The most significant LFI discussed has been implemented as auxiliary modules in clusterd, though they&amp;rsquo;re pretty trivial to exploit on their own.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>railo security - part two - post-authentication rce</title>
      <link>https://dronesec.pw/blog/railo-security-part-two-post-authentication-rce/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2014 15:10:04 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dronesec.pw/blog/railo-security-part-two-post-authentication-rce/</guid>
      <description>Part one - intro
Part two - post-authentication rce
Part three - pre-authentication lfi
Part four - pre-authentication rce
This post continues our dive into Railo security, this time introducing several post-authentication RCE vulnerabilities discovered in the platform. As stated in part one of this series, like ColdFusion, there is a task scheduler that allows authenticated users the ability to write local files. Whilst the existence of this feature sets it as the standard way to shell a Railo box, sometimes this may not work.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>railo security - part one - intro</title>
      <link>https://dronesec.pw/blog/railo-security-part-one-intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2014 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dronesec.pw/blog/railo-security-part-one-intro/</guid>
      <description>Part one - intro
Part two - post-authentication rce
Part three - pre-authentication lfi
Part four - pre-authentication rce
Railo is an open-source alternative to the popular Coldfusion application server, implementing a FOSSy CFML engine and application server. It emulates Coldfusion in a variety of ways, mainly features coming straight from the CF world, along with several of it&amp;rsquo;s own unique features (clustered servers, a plugin architecture, etc). In this four-part series, we&amp;rsquo;ll touch on how Railo, much like Coldfusion, can be used to gain access to a system or network of systems.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
