<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>rce on dronesec</title>
    <link>https://dronesec.net/categories/rce/</link>
    <description>Recent content in rce on dronesec</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Bryan Alexander</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 29 Jun 2014 15:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://dronesec.net/categories/rce/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>gitlist - commit to rce</title>
      <link>https://dronesec.net/blog/gitlist-commit-to-rce/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Jun 2014 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dronesec.net/blog/gitlist-commit-to-rce/</guid>
      <description>Gitlist is a fantastic repository viewer for Git; it&amp;rsquo;s essentially your own private Github without all the social networking and glitzy features of it. I&amp;rsquo;ve got a private Gitlist that I run locally, as well as a professional instance for hosting internal projects. Last year I noticed a bug listed on their Github page that looked a lot like an exploitable hole:
Oops! sh: 1: Syntax error: EOF in backquote substitution I commented on its exploitability at the time, and though the hole appears to be closed, the issue still remains.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>rce in browser exploitation framework (BeEF)</title>
      <link>https://dronesec.net/blog/rce-in-browser-exploitation-framework-beef/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2014 20:57:53 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dronesec.net/blog/rce-in-browser-exploitation-framework-beef/</guid>
      <description>Let me preface this post by saying that this vulnerability is already fixed, and was caught pretty early during the development process. The vulnerability was originally introduced during a merge for the new DNS extension, and was promptly patched by antisnatchor on 03022014. Although this vulnerability was caught fairly quickly, it still made it into the master branch. I post this only because I&amp;rsquo;ve seen too many penetration testers leaving their tools externally exposed, often with default credentials.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
